<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[J. Cachada Personal Website]]></title><description><![CDATA[A personal website for all of my j.cachada needs.]]></description><link>https://jcachada.dev</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 20:35:19 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Book Update #3: Balance in the opening, and the problem with exposition]]></title><description><![CDATA[After I finished the first draft and revised five thousand words last month, I set a lofty goal for this month’s book update. Unfortunately…]]></description><link>https://jcachada.dev/book-update-july-2020/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jcachada.dev/book-update-july-2020/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;After I finished the first draft and revised five thousand words last month, I set a lofty goal for this month’s book update. Unfortunately, things were a bit slower than I’d hoped, mainly due to certain problems that needed to be adressed in the starting chapters. The silver lining is that handling those problems allowed me to reflect on some aspects of the writing process for long enough that I can leverage them into a blog post. As always, if all you’re interested in is a word count update, feel free to jump to the end of this page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;And the Empire was huge - the problem with exposition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps one of the first pieces of advice every writer hears multiple times throughout the course of his career is &lt;em&gt;show, don’t tell&lt;/em&gt;. This “rule” is supposed to help you with making sure your prose isn’t hard to read. Quite often, especially in fantasy, young authors start with a healthy passion for the worlds their favorite authors built, from the dizzying expansiveness of Tolkien’s mythology to the intricacies of Brandon Sanderson’s magic systems. This passion is undoubtedly beneficial, and in no small part it is why people want to write. You see those myths, those people, those worlds, and you think to yourself: “maybe I could do that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But sometimes, in the quest to mimic those, depth can be confused with detail. On the one hand, the depth in Tolkien’s work comes as much from the sheer quantity of backstory he wrote for that world. On the other hand, if you were to read or watch &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt;, you probably wouldn’t know anything about Húrin - because you don’t have to know anything about Húrin to follow the story to the fullest, and because including that whole backstory would probably have harmed the story in other ways: for instance, by affecting its pacing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same is true of something like Brandon Sanderson’s books. The magic systems Sanderson cooks up are usually extremely detailed. Something like Allomancy has several internal rules that determine how everything functions in the internal logic of the universe. But if Sanderson started &lt;em&gt;Mistborn&lt;/em&gt; with an in-depth discussion of how Allomancy works, most readers would get bored pretty quickly. It’s hard to connect to a story unless something in it speaks to you, and the product of worldbuilding needs to be realized into avatars of sorts (characters or not) that cash in on all that work. It’s sort of like backend and frontend in software. The backend is running the show, and unless it’s well done things quite simply won’t work. But the frontend is what your users will interact with. Its quality determines how much they like your program or application, how good it feels to use. You can have the fastest backend in the world (in this analogy, this would mean Tolkien-esque worldbuilding), but if your frontend is just a console, people will choose to use prettier, snappier applications (in this analogy, the frontend would be your characters, your plot, anything you use to pass out the information to the readers in an appealing way). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my book, I have both an out of the ordinary setting, and an out of the ordinary magic system. Without getting too much into spoiler territory, the setting is one where being sad, miserable, or otherwise with a very serious case of the blues is a big no-no, bordering on a crime against the state. And the magic system that naturally follows is predicated on the concept of emotional manipulation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a pair of ideas that is at the core of much of the conflict and themes of the book, but very hard to execute properly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more alien the elements of the story are, the more explanation they need to make sure they don’t alienate the readers. Of course everyone likes originality, new settings, new concepts: but there is a balance to find in it where you have to layer the new concepts with familiarity, otherwise people will just be confused. If the characters in your story act, think, and feel nothing like the people we know and interact with, even if there’s a good logical reason for it, there’s a good chance a lot of the readers won’t be able to connect to them. And emotional connection is at the core of every good story. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was revising the first couple of chapters in my book, I realized some things related to this problem needed work. I didn’t really explain at all what the magic system was about until a bit later into the chapter, and I realized it could be quite frustrating to hear all the characters talk about it without having any idea what they meant. At the same time, I had to find a way to insert some explanation as to what the magic system was. I could have sat two characters down and made one of them explain everything to the other, but that seems sloppy and not very interesting; it would have just been a proxy for me to explain things directly to the reader. Instead, I added an entirely new scene before the story starts - a prologue of sorts - that tells a self-contained, quite short story about the consequences of using this magic system and how it affects people. I tell this short story through the eyes of the main character, but years before the main story of the book begins. I feel like it does a fairly good job of illustrating the magic system, the setting it exists in, and sets up some character traits for the main character, but does so with things happening in that front, instead of just doing it through exposition. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this prologue was new writing altogether, so it had to go through the whole process of writing, revising, then revising again. That’s the main reason things were a bit slower with the revision than I had thought - but I’m confident the book was made better for it, which is really all that matters in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’ll be quite interesting when I send the book to beta readers to actually see if they’re confused by what happens in the first few chapters or not, specifically when it comes to the setting and magic system. It’s hard for me to have the distance required to know whether or not things need further explanation, because I know how everything works already. It’s sort of how a power user won’t really notice that a menu is confusing, because he’s used it thousands of times before, so he knows where everything is. I’ve done my best to find a balance with this, but I won’t really know if it worked until I get other people’s opinion on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something tells me that, like much of my writing (and my creative endeavors in general), it’ll end up being mostly an iterative process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Current state of things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding the new scene and reworking exposition in the first few chapters required some new writing that slowed down the revision process. For this reason, I didn’t meet the word count goal for this month. However, I still revised a little over ten thousand words and tightened up the beginning of the book a lot. I will carry over the same goal for the month of July.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current word count&lt;/strong&gt;: 16.195 thousand words (second draft).
&lt;strong&gt;June goal&lt;/strong&gt;: Go up to 35 to 40 thousand words in the second draft.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Dev Diaries #3: July Update]]></title><description><![CDATA[Last month I said I was iterating on gameplay loops to try and find something that works for the game while I grind away at the book. This…]]></description><link>https://jcachada.dev/game-update-july-2020/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jcachada.dev/game-update-july-2020/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Last month I said I was iterating on gameplay loops to try and find something that works for the game while I grind away at the book. This month I will do my first actual implementation overview, and sort of go through the challenges of implementing the sort of 2D combat that you see traditionally in a lot of indie games. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Responsibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game is being developed on Godot Engine, and Godot uses the concept of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.godotengine.org/en/stable/getting_started/step_by_step/godot_design_philosophy.html&quot;&gt;scene tree.&lt;/a&gt; Understanding Godot’s design philosophy is extremely important to make sure things work properly in the end and you can assemble the different blocks in a single scene without everything being very cumbersome to change. From my understanding of it, the design rules for designing a game’s scenes are very similar to the design rules for designing, say, APIs. One of the most important questions you’ll have to answer in both is what the responsibilities are for specific classes. Generally speaking, in software, it’s a good idea to follow the &lt;em&gt;Single Responsibility Principle&lt;/em&gt; (SRP). According to Wikipedia, the SRP states that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;every module or class should have responsibility over a single part of the functionality provided by the software, and that responsibility should be entirely encapsulated by the class, module or function.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just a fancy way of saying that your classes should do one thing, and one thing alone. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Godot, the Scene’s responsibility is that of &lt;em&gt;orchestrating&lt;/em&gt; everything else. So, for a combat scenario where you have a character fighting a monster, the character and the monster handle themselves. They know when they get hit, when they’re supposed to change their animation, and in general can behave without input from other classes. But the scene is what controls everything they don’t know themselves; for instance, the GUI, their relative positions, and whatever information they need to react to that they don’t have in their own class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, let’s check what the composition was for the scene that I assembled containing the proof of concept for 2D combat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 650px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/bf17ede4c54fb34532c4d8b0d9265c16/f766a/scene-composition.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 49.079754601226995%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAKCAYAAAC0VX7mAAAACXBIWXMAABJ0AAASdAHeZh94AAAB80lEQVQoz22SSW/bMBCF9SeauvGWwna8yZsoMRJlW5sVSZQlG06R5mI0PTRA0VOB/v/XIQMYaZHDA0dD8tObGRq2kFg6CWYshOVlcPwSd5sKzrrEzAoxWW5JAaargM5E+ns4W2M0V9pgqDTzseQpON0z1OUgfcA6qpEXNeS+RpaXFCvtL1K57L+czCVkmkEWEtu4hIhOMOZ2qunupkCWFajrCtW+wuFIOlF8qFFVe8qRypLWUsd1KZE8PsF9foE8nZAkBcL7LzAWTgovoBJFhpyAh0oBD6jSLc4PC0TCgjceQ/QHtE7g3Q4hen1wc4Hu+Rc+ff8D89tPxHEBWxQwVC+mqxCmFWiHyk19PCJgDHfNJni7DbvVhnXdhPtwBCOo02hg1Rug+fQDV8+/MT2/IAjv0Z8IGKYVYzAV1FhBfZGv5RAwtG24N5/BSU6nC9bqgH99BDPncJotcPrJwlzi1g2wFWsk6R6Wm8FgXk7uIj3poij/ATJypWBKtgIWOzijkQaqHG/R+uEKMbOxiXJy6MFYubke/4hGn+dvHTqwlZPuzQXKO51LrEV7jJzGnGMdZuiNCcgEvTc70cC3DgOLYfWxoaHs+n2pPXUmIocXoHLoRwdd8utQaMo1vcldgsQTSHzqj/DfF+3FdEamO/jbFD0q+S+n21Asb1k2jAAAAABJRU5ErkJggg==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;image info&quot;
        title=&quot;Scene composition&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/bf17ede4c54fb34532c4d8b0d9265c16/663f3/scene-composition.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/bf17ede4c54fb34532c4d8b0d9265c16/5e043/scene-composition.png 163w,
/static/bf17ede4c54fb34532c4d8b0d9265c16/e5cc6/scene-composition.png 325w,
/static/bf17ede4c54fb34532c4d8b0d9265c16/663f3/scene-composition.png 650w,
/static/bf17ede4c54fb34532c4d8b0d9265c16/d880f/scene-composition.png 975w,
/static/bf17ede4c54fb34532c4d8b0d9265c16/4c573/scene-composition.png 1300w,
/static/bf17ede4c54fb34532c4d8b0d9265c16/f766a/scene-composition.png 1808w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see there are four main components in the scene: the player character, a monster (here represented by a nice little ghost), an obstacle in the form of a pillar, and the GUI controlling the player’s health and stamina.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping in line with what I mentioned before, let’s look at what the code looks like in the actual scene’s file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-python&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot;&gt;func _ready&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	$Player&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;start&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;$PlayerStartPosition&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;position&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; true&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	$Mob&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;start&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;$PlayerStartPosition&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;position&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	$CombatGUI&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;updateHealth&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	$CombatGUI&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;updateStamina&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	
func _on_Mob_shoot&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bullet&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; pos&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;## Spawns the bullet, makes it move, and rotates it to move towards the player.&lt;/span&gt;
	var b &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; bullet&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;instance&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	add_child&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;b&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	var &lt;span class=&quot;token builtin&quot;&gt;dir&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; Vector2&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;rotated&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;$Mob&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;position&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;angle_to_point&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;$Player&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;global_position&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	b&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;start&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;pos&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token builtin&quot;&gt;dir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

func _on_Player_update_Healthbar&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;health&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	$CombatGUI&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;updateHealth&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;health&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three things here: first, the ready function, that starts the whole scene. It spawns the player at a particular position, does the same for the mob, and sets the GUI to show full health and stamina. The player and the mob both control their own health - it wouldn’t make any sense for the scene orchestrating them to control it. But it does make sense for the scene to orchestrate the GUI to match the player’s health, and since the player class always spawns the player at full health and stamina when instanced, we can just set the GUI to show full health and stamina. In a full production level, we could make the scene set the GUI values to &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;$Player.currentHealth&lt;/code&gt; instead of 100.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second function is &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;on_Mob_shoot&lt;/code&gt;. You might be wondering why spawning the bullet that the monster shoots is the responsibility of the scene, and not the responsibility of the monster. The easy reply is that the monster class doesn’t have all the information required to spawn the bullet itself. The bullet needs to be spawned pointing towards the player character’s position, and the monster has no idea what the player character’s position is. Besides, the monster has to spawn the bullet in a specific position in the actual scene, and the only class that can do that is the scene itself. If the monster is the child of the scene, and the bullet is a child of the scene too - one that will exist and behave independently of the monster - then the bullet needs to be a child of the scene as well, and not a child of the monster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, there is &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;_on_Player_update_Healthbar&lt;/code&gt;. This function, like the last one, is a signal - meaning it triggers when something else happens that emits the signal this function is listening for. In this case, the trigger would be the player’s health updating. If the player knows that it got shot, and updates his own health accordingly, then the scene, that has control of the GUI, should make sure the GUI reflects the update in the player’s health. If we were doing stamina management as well, there should be another function listening in for when the player updates his own stamina. However, for the proof of concept, there is still no stamina management implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won’t give a detailed look into the Player class in this game, mainly because I feel like it deserves a blog post of its own in the future. In rough terms, the Player class takes input from the user and can move and attack. Besides that, it can take damage, and it will die if it takes too much of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will, however, go into a big challenge that I found when implementing the Monster class: pathfinding, or enemy AI in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pathfinding AI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic behavior I wanted from the monster was that it would chase the player around and shoot it whenever it got close enough. This was mostly easy to implement, except for one thing: pathfinding. Remember the pillar in the middle of the scene? Making the monster move in a straight line towards the player was easy enough, but making the monster calculate the best possible path if the player hid behind a pillar was actually very challenging. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s get right into it. This is how things ended up looking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-python&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot;&gt;	
func _process&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;delta&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; mobHealth &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
		queue_free&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; stopMoving&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# The start position for the pathfinding is the mob&apos;s current position.&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# The goal position for the pathfinding is the player&apos;s current position.&lt;/span&gt;
	
	startPosition &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; position
	endPosition &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; player&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;position
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;player&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;position&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;x &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; position&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;x&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; 
		$ProperAnimation&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;flip_h &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; true&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
		$ProperAnimation&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;flip_h &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; false&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	_update_path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
		var to_walk &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; delta &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; speed
		&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; to_walk &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
			var pfrom &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
			var pto &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
			var d &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; pfrom&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;distance_to&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;pto&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; d &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; to_walk&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
				path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;remove&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
				to_walk &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-=&lt;/span&gt; d
			&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
				path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; pfrom&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;linear_interpolate&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;pto&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; to_walk&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;d&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
				to_walk &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
		
		var atpos &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
		position &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; atpos
		
		&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
			path &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
			set_process&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;false&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
		set_process&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;false&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;## Calculates a new path using the available Navigation 2D node. The startPosition and endPosition are updated every frame on the process function.&lt;/span&gt;
	
func _update_path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	var p &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; navigation&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;get_simple_path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;startPosition&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; endPosition&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; true&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	path &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; Array&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;p&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# PoolVector2Array too complex to use, convert to regular array&lt;/span&gt;
	path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;invert&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	set_process&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;true&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oof, that’s a lot to unpack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;_process&lt;/code&gt; function. This is a function that runs on every frame that the game renders. It’s useful for things that need to constantly be recalculated, like, for instance, what the best path to take is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing we do is check if the mob should be moving or not. This is a simple flag to add that can save a lot of computation later. If the mob shouldn’t be moving, there is no need to do any path calculation whatsoever, so we can make sure we’re not using any processing power doing that if the flag says it’s not needed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, we determine where the monster needs to move from, and where it needs to move to. It needs to go from where it currently is (that’s the start position) to where the player is at the time of the calculation (that’s the end position).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows is a simple animation check to deal with the sprites. If the player is to the left of the monster, we need to make sure the sprite is facing left. If the player is to the right of the monster, we need to make sure the sprite is facing right. Otherwise, the monster would look like it’s moonwalking towards the player sometimes. It’s a ghost, but it has no eyes on its back! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, we jump to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;updatePath()&lt;/code&gt; function. This was the saving grace of my development process. I tried for hours to find a way to algorithmically calculate what the best way to dodge a specific obstacle would be for the monster. Among other things, I tried:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having collision boxes on the obstacles and the monster. When the monster met an object, it would calculate the distance it was between itself and the top and the bottom of the obstacle, then it would try to go around it through the shortest possible path. This didn’t work very well for situations where there were multiple obstacles: the monster would try to go around one, then bump into another, try to go around that one, and end up moving away from the player instead of taking a different path that was a bit longer but allowed it to actually chase its prey.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having the monster hit the obstacles at a slight angle. This way, it would sort of slide off the pillar and eventually be able to move around it before continuing to chase the player in a straight line. This also didn’t work great with multiple obstacles, because then the monster could easily get stuck if there was no place it could slide to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s when I found out about &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.godotengine.org/en/stable/classes/class_navigation2d.html&quot;&gt;Navigation2D.&lt;/a&gt;. It turns out Godot already provided the functionality of pathfinding I wanted to implement: all I needed to do was create a Navigation2D node and declare what the “walkable” area of the scene was. Any area outside that wouldn’t be considered valid for pathfinding purposes, making the monster path around it. I added a Navigation2D that excluded the pillar, and made the monster update its own path by checking that node instead of trying to calculate it programatically. The &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;update_path&lt;/code&gt; function then returns an array of points the monster would have to move to in sequence in order to reach the player.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the process function just executes on that array, by moving to each point in sequence while there are points to move to. This movement can now be in a straight line, because the points themselves will already illustrate the path that the monster needs to move around. If there aren’t any points left to move to, the monster just stops moving. There is a collision box checking when it is close enough to the player and toggling the “stop moving” flag when the monster is close enough to shoot, so the monster never actually runs out of path to follow; what happens is that when it gets close enough, it stops processing the path. When the player leaves the monster’s range, the flag gets toggled, and the monster begins processing the path again on every frame. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what it looks like in motion:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/3dbb8b42b088bd66bf123328e4eb70d4/working2DCombat.gif&quot; alt=&quot;image info&quot; title=&quot;Working POC&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Back to responsibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you were paying attention, you might have noticed the reason I had the bullets be spawned by the scene itself, instead of by the monster, is that the monster should have no idea what the relative position of the player is. But in my implementation of the moving algorithm, I use the player’s current position as the end position for the monster’s &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;_process&lt;/code&gt; function! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You would be right to notice this. This is, in fact, a good indication that calculating the path should be a responsibility of the scene. Most likely, the monster should only have a function named &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;move()&lt;/code&gt; that receives an array of positions, and executes on it; while calculating the content of that array of positions should be done by the scene, because it has all the information required to do so, whereas the monster shouldn’t. Imagine we wanted to spawn a monster in a scene with no player: the way things are implemented above, we’d have to create a new Monster implementation, because it would break when trying to use the player’s end position. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of the proof of concept, I decided not to change this, and to let it live as a reminder of how proper design often comes from iteration. If I was developing the actual end product, that would be a necessary change going forward. For now, I think it’s more important for me to start looking at other aspects of the game, and to polish the design of whatever gameplay loop I end up going with in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Acknowledgement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the assets you see in the proof of concept are free assets I’m using for mocking purposes, and they come from itch.io. You can find several free asset packs to work with there, although most of them require crediting if you end up using them in your end products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next month I’ll either write a new blog post on the implementation of another core system or, if I make any progress on the proof of concept for other gameplay loops, outline those, much like I did here for 2D combat. As usual, the development of the game is somewhat slowed, as the book takes precedence this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions, comments or feedback, feel free to reach out to me through any of the channels I make available in the About page; and if you want to give a more in-depth look to the code, you can check my github, linked in the footer. Bear in mind all of this details my journey in self-teaching both Godot and game development, so I’m sure some of the ways I handle things are not optimal. It’s part of the learning process.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Book Update #2: Second Drafting, plot cohesion, and titles]]></title><description><![CDATA[I am glad to say I am done with the first draft of the book. It took me longer than I expected it to (perhaps my predictions are a bit…]]></description><link>https://jcachada.dev/book-update-june-2020/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jcachada.dev/book-update-june-2020/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I am glad to say I am done with the first draft of the book. It took me longer than I expected it to (perhaps my predictions are a bit optimistic), but it is done. I am glad with what I came up with and have started a second passthrough and first revision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While my first draft was all about getting the story on paper and making sure I had it all vomited out, the second draft requires a bit more finesse. As I finished my first draft, I was immediately afforded with a lot of clarity. Now that I had a full, bird’s eye view of the story that I wanted to tell, it was easier to look at the individual chapters and scenes and realize things that didn’t fit or that needed to be changed. Throughout the process of writing the first draft I also kept a journal of every thing that I noticed as I went along and wanted to mark as “review this later”. This was a way to shut up my inner editor for long enough that I could actually get anything done. But now that I’m done with the first draft, it’s time to address these concerns - so, besides adjusting some plot points, I’ll also be reworking some scenes and massively improving the language, sentence construction, atmosphere… Really, everything about the novel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I once heard a famous author (I want to say Neil Gaiman, but am not fully certain) say that the first draft was when you wrote, and the second draft was when you made it look like you had any idea what you were doing the first time around. The second draft is where the magic is going to happen, and I’m super excited to take the time to polish up my scenes and make them as good and immersive as I can. I’ve already started working on some dialogues in the first chapter and I think they’re coming out a lot better this time around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing you might have noticed is that I’ve added a tentative title of &lt;strong&gt;“The Life Collectors”&lt;/strong&gt; to the home page of the website. This is not a final title, I want to make that very clear. But I figured it was time I started thinking about it, and that it gave everything a bit more of a professional look if I removed “Untitled Book” from the homepage. Titles are hard for me to come up with, so I’m trying some and seeing how interesting they are and if any of them sticks until I’m done with the book. Maybe it’ll be “The Life Collectors”, but most likely the title will still change several times until I land on something. We’ll see on the next update, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for keeping up with what I’ve been doing, and I hope I can get my work to you soon. I can’t wait for you to read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Current state of things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it stands, I’m about 5 thousand words in and working on the second draft  as outlined above. Considering that I want to have this book finished this year, and that there’s still a part of the process missing involving beta readers, I’m going to kick things up to eleven and set a goal for this month of revising at least 35, but ideally 40 thousand words of the first draft. This will take a lot of time if I want to make sure that the quality remains high, but it’s a challenge I want to impose on myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current word count&lt;/strong&gt;: 5 thousand words (second draft).
&lt;strong&gt;June goal&lt;/strong&gt;: Revise 35 to 40 thousand words.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Dev Diaries #2: June Update]]></title><description><![CDATA[This will unfortunately be a very short dev diary, and it’ll serve only as an update as to what’s been going on.  As outlined in my latest…]]></description><link>https://jcachada.dev/game-update-june-2020/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jcachada.dev/game-update-june-2020/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This will unfortunately be a very short dev diary, and it’ll serve only as an update as to what’s been going on. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As outlined in my latest Book Update, I’ve been making a lot of progress with the book and am trying to meet my personal goal of having it fully done this year. Like I said in my mission statement, the book will take precedence over the game until it is done. So, this month I got a lot of work done on the book, and not a lot of work done on the game. I started working on the proof of concept for sidescrolling combat, and implemented it (you can see it on github), but did not address any of the other possible gameplay mechanics. Hopefully I’ll be able to make some progress on at least one of them this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll make a more detailed post on implementing basic sidescrolling combat soon, but for now this is all the updates on the state of the game for the month of June. If you were more interested in the game than in the book, I’m sorry, but I’ve always made it very clear that the book is my priority for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to see you back again soon with more meaningful updates for the game’s development!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Dev Diaries #1: Finding a Gameplay Loop]]></title><description><![CDATA[I understand stories better than I understand game design. That’s the crux of current problem with developing my game. I know precisely what…]]></description><link>https://jcachada.dev/finding-a-gameplay-loop/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jcachada.dev/finding-a-gameplay-loop/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I understand stories better than I understand game design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the crux of current problem with developing my game. I know precisely what story I want to tell and what themes I want to approach - but any game must have a somewhat defined recurring gameplay loop which makes up for the bulk of the player’s experience. Coming up with that central gameplay loop is harder than it sounds, at least for me. In this post I’ll attempt to make clear what my thought process is on this matter, and why I don’t just slap some gameplay onto the game. I will also attempt to make this post into a decision log of sorts, where I lay out the options I’ve identified so far and their respective pros and cons. Hopefully this process will introduce some clarity, or at the very least it will serve as an historical document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to aim for&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, the central gameplay loop must be enjoyable. This might seem like a very obvious thing to say, but I think it’s important that this is the first consideration. Above all, players must like playing the game. I have often seen games put their intended message and artistic merit above player enjoyment. Just recently I played a very interesting narrative driven game that was riddled with issues because it just wasn’t fun to play, even though the story was very engaging. While I can’t presume to know how the development process went for that particular game, I definitely felt like they made the game serve the story they wanted to tell, and came up with something that just wasn’t enjoyable to play; or at least, not for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t to say gameplay can’t serve the narrative. Visual novels and walking simulators, for instance, are enjoyable to the audience they target, explicitly because the gameplay, simple as it may be, serves a particular purpose to enable the narrative and experience they want to provide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to my second point: the gameplay must be coherent with the narrative themes, and ideally enhance them. At the very least, it shouldn’t directly contradict them. &lt;em&gt;Undertale&lt;/em&gt; would be a much worse game if, instead of a dodging game reminiscent of old SHMUP experiences, it had traditional 2D side scrolling combat. Ideally, the gameplay loop would directly tie into the narrative experience and enhance it: &lt;em&gt;Dark Souls&lt;/em&gt;, for instance, is a game for which a brutal, opressive combat system decidedly makes sense, and enhances the brutal, opressive atmosphere of a decaying world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third point is a bit more controversial: it should be in some way new. That doesn’t mean coming up with some new way of interacting with the game entirely. New gameplay mechanics are hard to come by, and the returns on coming up with them are often diminished by the learning curve required with having to introduce players to new mechanics. Everyone can play a platformer: the collective cultural experience that everyone sort of has about video games makes a platformer very easy to understand. But that doesn’t mean you can’t improve on &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Brothers 2&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, a more personal point. If my central focus is narrative, I could just pick an existing gameplay loop and implement the one that better served the narrative I want to tell. And I might still do just that - but if I do, I personally want to iterate on it in some way. Game development is not only a narrative process in artistic terms, but also a creative process in terms of the actual game aspect of it. I don’t think I’d be happy with my game if I didn’t try to improve upon whichever gameplay loop I end up choosing, even if it’s just a small incremental improvement. I strongly believe in iteration: even mechanics as simple as those found in walking simulators can be improved upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to sum up, here’s what I’m looking for in terms of the main gameplay loop is:&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;ol style=&quot;padding-left:30px&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An enjoyable gameplay loop that...&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;... Does not directy contradict, and ideally enhances the narrative experience, while...&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;... Improving upon at least some of the existing implementations of similar gameplay loops. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, let’s go through each gameplay loop I think is available to me and try to figure out some pros and cons for each one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Card Game or Card / Puzzle Game Hybrid&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering I was once a professional card game player, designing a card game would probably be my first instinct. It’s a subject I know very well, it’s something I can be reasonably creative in, while not feeling completely out of my depth. It’s also something that would not be tremendously hard to implement on the tech side. Like with sidescrolling combat, the hardest thing to implement would almost surely be enemy AI, but even then there are excellent resources available on how to implement card game enemy AI: &lt;em&gt;Prismata&lt;/em&gt;, for instance, has done excellent work on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, a card game is generally not suited to single-player narrative driven experiences, considering how dependent the genre is on stuff like evolving metas and deckbuilding capabilities. Fortunately, games like &lt;em&gt;Thronebreaker: The Witcher Tales&lt;/em&gt; have already introduced a puzzle / card game hybrid that maintains some of the best things about card games (the puzzles, trying to decide what the correct play at any given time is) that works well for single-player.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see two cons to this main gameplay loop. First of all is that it doesn’t seem to serve the narrative in any way. The game is broadly about corruption vs kindness, and how people react in desperate situations. To do it with a card game would imply finding a way to make the gameplay play to those themes. While possible, this isn’t immediately easy or obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second con is the art expense. Card games in general have excellent art. &lt;em&gt;Magic The Gathering&lt;/em&gt;’s art is legendary, &lt;em&gt;Gwent&lt;/em&gt; had extremely high quality art, and in general the card game audience has very high expectations in what concerns the quality of their card art. This would make it hard to meet those expectations with my available funds: after all, top tier artists are expensive, a card game demands a very high quantity of good art, and this is an indie, hobby level project. The investment would not just be hard to justify, but hard to make happen in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Walking Simulator / Visual Novel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When one wants to make a game and call it narrative-driven, there is always the question of whether or not to make it limited in actual gameplay mechanics, and make it instead a visual novel or a walking simulator. Those games are, in fact, often associated with a heavier focus on narrative, because there are no other mechanics in it to compete with the story: the game lives and dies on its plot and characters. I include in this section games that have very limited gameplay mechanics, like &lt;em&gt;To The Moon&lt;/em&gt;, which I love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest con for this type of approach is the “enjoyable” bullet point. A lot of people just don’t like visual novels. Walking simulators are a polarizing genre, with people often arguing they’re not even games. If I wanted to maximize the audience I can reach, perhaps walking simulators and visual novels needlessly restrict me from the getgo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, I don’t think making decisions based on whether or not something is too niche is particularly productive, especially because I’m someone trying to develop a game I’m proud of, and not a mega-corporation trying to maximize profits. Because of that, the central question is just whether or not I’d be happy making a walking sim or a visual novel. They tend to be less challenging on the technical aspect than other games, and while I coded systems like saved games myself (instead of using engines like Ren’Py), I feel like I’d still have to find ways to challenge myself with new features and ways to iterate on the visual novel / walking sim formula to be happy with the end product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Platformer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t particularly enjoy platformers, so it’s easy for me to dismiss this option, as I want to work on something I’m personally engaged by. However, for the sake of the exercise, I’ll still go through the pros and cons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Platformers are easy to iterate on and there’s tons of stuff I could introduce to try and make the experience varied and unique. They also have a very large amount of data available on how to code different aspects, available from different games and their tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the con side, they’re probably the most overcrowded genre on the indie market right now. Everyone makes platformers, and lots of players aren’t willing to give yet another new platformer a try. They want something new. If I wanted to make a platformer, I’d have to find a differentiating factor, like &lt;em&gt;Ori and the Blind Forest&lt;/em&gt; did with its artstyle. But it would have to come from the mechanics side of it, as I would never have the budget to throw at the game to make it stand out on its art alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2D Roguelike Combat: Either Side-scrolling or Top-Down&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was my initial instinct when starting the development process. It just felt natural to me, and I feel like that comes from an inclination that I have from my playing experiences: that having bad guys you fight with several different tools is the basic gameplay loop mostly everyone is familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some downsides, however. The technical aspect of coding combat can be seen as a boon and a challenge. It took me almost a month to code a basic enemy AI that just chases the player character around shooting stuff at him when it gets within a certain range. This is a very slow pace, and combat AI is something it’d take me a long time to learn and code, probably. I’ve looked into how games like Rimworld and Left 4 Dead 2 do their AIs, and there’s a lot to unpack there. But even though it might be biting off more than I can chew, I also can’t help but feel excited by it. It’s an interesting subject, and one I’d like to try and tackle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the biggest downside besides that is the animation cost. Whereas other genres would have limited costs in terms of walking / jumping animations for the characters and then punctual cost for special animations as needed, a combat-heavy game would have exponentially higher cost: animations for every mob, their different moves, the player character’s different moves, potential new weapons… All of this would have to be purchased, or I’d have to learn to draw it myself. Either way this would mean a large increase in the development cost for the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, now that I’ve listed the options… What comes next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next month, and until it is done, my priority will be the book I’ve been working on for the last year. That means that, when my time is limited and I have to choose, I’ll work on the book first, and only give the game my full attention when the book is done. The reason I say this is that I’m fully aware that I might not finish what I’m about to propose in time, and that’s okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the next steps will be building a Proof of Concept for each of the gamemodes above, and try and see how I’d implement them in a scene. In that scene, focus on how I’d try and answer some of the questions I asked myself here, like the questions about differentiation for some of the genres. With the working POCs in hand I’ll be able to make a more informed decision on which path to take for the entire game. Perhaps I’ll even find a compromise and use bits and pieces of them. Time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that’s the deliverable for the next dev diary: I’ll report back on how the development is going for the different POCs, with the forewarning that they’ll be on the back burner until I’m done with the book.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Book Update #1: First Drafting]]></title><description><![CDATA[I’ve written a lot of “books”, all of them absolute garbage and nothing I want to ever see the light of day.  Some of them were bad because…]]></description><link>https://jcachada.dev/book-update-may-2020/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jcachada.dev/book-update-may-2020/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’ve written a lot of “books”, all of them absolute garbage and nothing I want to ever see the light of day. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of them were bad because I was too young to know any better. Some of them were bad because I hadn’t had enough practice to iron out some kinks in my writing. And some of them were bad because I didn’t work on them enough. Something which I’ve come to understand is that I’ve written a lot of books, but I haven’t finished a lot of them. That’s because I skipped one of the main steps: editing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone said once that editing is when you make it look like you knew what the hell you were doing when you wrote your first draft. I find that to be an accurate description. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I look back at all the stuff I’ve written before, I see a lot of potential in it, but no coherent solid body of work. That’s because I didn’t take the time to edit it appropriately, to gain some distance and then look on it and try to improve it with a bird’s eye view of the entire story. I sort of just went at it and wrote. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s why with this book I’m expecting to take the rest of this year to call it “done”, even though I’m almost done with the first draft before the year reaches the halfway mark. I will then have to let it rest for a slight while, do an entire readthrough with a plot edit, then do some line editing and correct any typos or weird wordings, then send it out to beta readers and adjust according to feedback. Yes, that’s a formal outline of the steps the book will have to go through for me to consider it done. I expect to be done with all these steps this year still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, a lot of the updates will simply illustrate how far along this path I am. Therefore, they’ll be quite short, unless I come up across some problem or subject I find interesting and want to talk about. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these stages will also imply a lower level of involvment on my end. When that happens, I’ll take the extra time to give some of my other projects attention, like my ongoing videogame. However, to make it perfectly clear, the book will always take priority, as it is my main goal for this year. I will only look at other stuff when my input is not needed on the book or when I have extra time remaining: for instance, when I’m waiting on beta reader feedback. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Current state of things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it stands, I’m about 110.000 words in and working on the first draft of what I expect to be the last couple of chapters. I want to hopefully finish the first draft this month, although that might be a slightly ambitious goal. We’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current word count&lt;/strong&gt;: 103.810 words
&lt;strong&gt;Current goal&lt;/strong&gt;: Finish first draft.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mission Statement: This blog, the website, and more.]]></title><description><![CDATA[In 2013, I went to college. I didn’t really know what I wanted to go to college for, and I ended up choosing Philosophy as a major because I…]]></description><link>https://jcachada.dev/mission-statement/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jcachada.dev/mission-statement/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 18:57:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In 2013, I went to college. I didn’t really know what I wanted to go to college for, and I ended up choosing Philosophy as a major because I thought it would give me a broad spectrum of skills and sort of postpone the actual decision of what I wanted to do with my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophy is a great major. I’m very grateful for the things that I learned during my time studying it, and I wish the state of humanities’ academia in Portugal wasn’t such that even the most skilled of students have no place at universities and aren’t particularly valued by the private sector. But that was the case, and I soon realized that I would have a very hard time finding a job related to my studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not, however, someone who likes to wait idly for things to get better. So I tried to figure out how I could leverage my work and the things that I liked into a proper career. At first that meant getting a Master’s in American Literature and American Culture. I thought I could at least get a job as a translator while I looked for something better, and surely a Master’s degree completed with honors would mean something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before I could give academia a real try, I realized what I was actually passionate about. In my Philosophy B.A., I specialized in Logics. In my Master’s, I gave special emphasis to American Literature. What do those have in common, and what do they have in common with what I ended up doing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion I came to was that what I really liked was stories; and that I wanted to do something related to them in some way, shape or faction. But I also found that working as a literature analyst was in a way oppressive. I missed seeing the real impact of the things I was doing, and it can be hard at times with literature to be sure what you do matters. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s when I started coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My skills in Logics, that I’d gotten during my BA, helped me a lot with getting into code. I did a bootcamp, I practiced a lot, and I found out that not only was I good at it and enjoyed the puzzle solving, as well as the fact that my code’s impact in the world was often clear and measurable, writing code was actually quite a bit like storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coding as Storytelling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I wrote and, especially, read more code, I realized a great part of the problems in programming came down to mistakes in communication, ambiguities that weren’t properly removed, things being overly verbose, or problems in a similar vein. Most production level systems ran by competent teams don’t really have critical level bugs that are caused by a massive oversight in logics, or someone entirely missing the logical foundation for a problem. Processes like code reviews, thorough testing habits, and general good practices do a good job of curbing those. Yet the problems I found the most often were the ones that eluded code reviews, because people no longer paid attention to them; the ones that got through testing, because it wasn’t clear what the test was doing, and we thought that a condition was being tested when it wasn’t; or the ones that don’t trigger the alarms because people simply don’t notice them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code must be readable. Not just to save the time of developers that come after and try to read it, but because if it isn’t, they won’t read it properly. And that will invariably lead to lost time, money, mental health, and generally a bunch of really avoidable problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s generally not very controversial to say that code must be readable, and I’m glad that’s the case - even though executing on this principle is often harder than naming it. But I think we should go a step further, and say not just that code must be readable: it must be &lt;em&gt;engaging&lt;/em&gt;. People pay more attention to books they find interesting. People pay more attention to code they’re engaged by. If your code is readable, but not particularly engaging, you run the risk of people’s mind drifting, and them missing something important in your code. When I started coding after years of researching literature, I tried to apply several principles of how you make a good story to how I write my code - to generally good results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of the following code I wrote for one of my games to handle an enemy’s movement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-python&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot;&gt;func _process&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;delta&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; mobHealth &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
		queue_free&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; stopMoving&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	
	startPosition &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; position
	endPosition &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; player&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;position
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;player&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;position&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;x &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; position&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;x&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; 
		$ProperAnimation&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;flip_h &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; true&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
		$ProperAnimation&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;flip_h &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; false&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	_update_path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
		var to_walk &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; delta &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; speed
		&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; to_walk &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
			var pfrom &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
			var pto &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
			var d &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; pfrom&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;distance_to&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;pto&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; d &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; to_walk&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
				path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;remove&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
				to_walk &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-=&lt;/span&gt; d
			&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
				path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; pfrom&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;linear_interpolate&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;pto&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; to_walk&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;d&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
				to_walk &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
		
		var atpos &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
		position &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; atpos
		
		&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
			path &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you get into the actual logics of things, I bet you lost interest halfway through the function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you try and tell a story with it and do so by extracting the logic in order to not harm the story’s flow with a tangent, this is what you get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-python&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot;&gt;func _process&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;delta&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; mobHealth &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
		queue_free&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; stopMoving&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

	startPosition &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; position
	endPosition &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; player&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;position
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;player&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;position&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;x &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; position&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;x&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; 
		$ProperAnimation&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;flip_h &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; true&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
		$ProperAnimation&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;flip_h &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; false&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	_update_path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	moveThroughPath&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

func moveThroughPath&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
		var to_walk &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; delta &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; speed
		&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; to_walk &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
			var pfrom &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
			var pto &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
			var d &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; pfrom&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;distance_to&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;pto&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; d &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; to_walk&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
				path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;remove&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
				to_walk &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-=&lt;/span&gt; d
			&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
				path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; pfrom&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;linear_interpolate&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;pto&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; to_walk&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;d&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
				to_walk &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
		
		var atpos &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
		position &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; atpos
		
		&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; path&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;size&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
			path &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way you declutter the actual method that’s telling the story - and whoever’s invested in it enough to want to get into the nitty gritty, instead of just getting an idea of how the system works, can go to the secondary method ´moveThroughPath´ and find out. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t revolutionary. Lots of very well established names in programming advocate for similar results through other names - for instance, Robert C. Martin’s &lt;em&gt;Clean Code&lt;/em&gt; argues in favor of a similar extraction on the basis that functions should have a single responsibility, and orchestration is already a responsibility. If you follow that rule, you generally get similar results. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I haven’t often seen it formulated in terms of storytelling. Perhaps because it’s less useful to people that don’t have my background or a similar interest in stories. For me, it helps to think of code that way. You wouldn’t want a novel to suddenly stop the thread of the main intrigue in its path to tell you about how the main character’s sword was made. So why should code break the narrative flow in such a way? Thinking of code in this way has allowed me to translate a lot of my skills in other areas to the activity of writing code. Of course, there’s more that I use in my day to day - I have a deep understanding of complex logics which helps with the algorithmic aspects of code, and the communication and speech skills acquired by reading, presenting at conferences, etc have a real practical application in the software world, where you must and should still interact effectively with people. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mission statement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the above, the mission statement shouldn’t come as a surprise. I want to write good stories. I want to &lt;em&gt;tell&lt;/em&gt; good stories. Stories are fundamentally a way to connect with other people, and I believe code acts as a facilitator for precisely that. Good code lets people connect, be it by enabling thriving businesses or by letting developers separated by time, different backgrounds and different interests to read code they didn’t write, add to it, and build something together. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s not to say I’ve forgotten stories themselves. As much as I love coding, I also like writing. And I want to connect with people in ways that are meaningful to me, and in ways that people have connected with me and impacted me before. That’s why I also write actual novels and short stories, and why I take an active interest in game development as a medium for telling stories. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll post about writing, software engineering, game development, and general life. This will function as my personal hub on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stories are my passion. You can explore mine in this website. I look forward to connecting with you! &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>